INTERNATIONAL SPACE STATION
MARS PILGRIM 7 MISSION
DAY 1
This is Dr Miranda North, Quarantine officer
aboard the International Space Station.
Today the Pilgrim capsule with
it's valuable Mars soil samples
completes it's 8 month
return from Mars.
Preparing to receive these samples
has been the purpose of our
mission these last few months.
But the Pilgrim capsule is damaged.
At 06:30 UTC
Pilgrim was struck by debris
and veered off course.
Rory Adams will space walk
to establish visual contact
with the incoming space capsule
and he will grab it
with the remote arm.
We've been waiting a long
time for this sample
and Rory is placing himself
at great risk to secure it.
- Over and out.
- EMU report: 4.7 psi, pure O2.
So how you gonna do it?
I wouldn't do it that way.
- Dr Jordan.
- Faster, faster, faster...
Nitrogen is zero.
- Dr North? I'm in the airlock.
- Faster, faster.. come on.
- Rory, slow to go fast.
- Or fast to go fast.
- Deliberate.
- We're here to get fast.
Remember, 8 billion people.
Rory, if you can't save it...
Yeah, spoiler alert!
I'm fucking saving it!
But if you can't, just push the capsule
into deep space, ok? Do you hear me?
Can you get OCD, sorry,
CDC, out of my face?
'Cause if I got a big operation,
I need to concentrate.
- I just want you...
- I can't, I can't hear you...
- I love you too.
- At all.
- EMU at 4.7 psi, pure O2.
- Where is the remote?
- Here. The arm is yours, full manual.
- All right, here we go.
- Careful with.. sorry, you know this.
- Yeah, I got it.
- No more sorries.
- Miranda, to the cupola, please.
Yep.
- David, are you on your way?
- On my way.
- Slow, Sho.
- Excuse me.
How you say "breath" in Japanese?
This was supposed to be a routine.
The air lock is sealed.
I.. am.. walking.
04:35 UTC. After striking
debris, Pilgrim non-responsive.
Inbound on a collision
course with the ISS.
Initiate emergency course
correction and manual retrieval.
Cannon armed online.
Transferring control to wireless.
Station to Control.
Initiating sequence.
Affirmative.
- So, the committee?
- You let me worry about the committee.
Where's Rory?
- He is at risk out there.
- Easy folks, mics are live.
- Ready, Sho?
- Thrusters up.
Holding in position.
I have control of the arm.
Your worry lines are showing.
Yeah, well, I get paid by the line.
- I have a good feeling about this.
- Yeah?
- Rory is gonna deliver that sample.
- Right to your lab.
Prepare for course correction.
.0509 .076
- Remember your training.
- We never trained for this!
On my mark!
- New capsule trajectory, negative 0.50.
- Proximity alert. Proximity alert.
Ignore the proximity alert.
New station trajectory: negative 0.32.
The capsule will miss us, just.
- Rory?
- I still don't reach.
It's coming in shallow.
Any moment now.
8, maybe 9 clock.
I'm having fun.
You guys having fun?
Rory..
- if you miss...
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
If...
Just gonna skip off the atmosphere,
like a flat stone on water.
Just fly off into nowhere,
no harm done.
Okay.
There!
- There.
- I see it.
All right. Here we go, here we go...
This is fun.
- Rory, you have to move, it's gonna hit you.
- That's bad.
Please Rory, move.
Station to Control. Visual
confirmation of Mars Capsule Pilgrim.
I used to play catcher,
but only in T-ball.
- Rory?
- Not now.
Not now. Come here, come here,
come on, come on...
Rory?
- Rory?
He caught it!
Hugh...
Cue Instagram!
I didn't wanna jinx it.
- Point and shoot, motherfucker!
- Okay.
Mars Capsule in lock position.
I'm coming home.
This is mission commander,
Ekaterina Golovkina.
Tell the committee, Pilgrim's landed
on Plymouth rock.
The Mars samples are safe and sound.
Copy that, Commander.
Congratulations.
ISS , DAY 2
Ready?
We are recording.
06:40 UTC.
Pilgrim wasn't just seeing
things in the Mars soil.
We are looking at a large
single cell. Inert.
Unmistakably biological.
And like organisms on Earth,
it has what appears to be a nucleus...
cytoplasm.
The cell wall is thick.
Those hairs look like cilia. Longer
than we're used to seeing on Earth.
More like flagella.
- What's the temperature?
- Minus 110.
Start bringing it up.
Minus 82.
Even quicker.
Minus 55.
This is some Re-Animator shit.
Oh, that's a very obscure reference.
- Not for a nerd.
- Not if you're a nerd.
Minus 17.
- Zero degrees.
- Oh, come on...
20 degrees Celsius.
Nothing.
Update?
I'm gonna try a different atmosphere.
Closer to Proterozoic Earth
than today's Mars.
Less oxygen
more carbon dioxide.
And then, when Sho is ready,
a growth medium.
In this case, glucose.
Come on, dance.
Did it just move?
Hugh?
My God.
It worked. You woke it.
We are looking at the first incontrovertible
proof of life beyond Earth.
Oh, it's beautiful.
Our first question is from Allen.
He is 9 years old.
And Allen, what is your question
for Commander Golovkina?
Is it green?
It's not visible at all actually,
it's microscopic. A single cell.
To put it into perspective,
your body is made up of trillions.
There is an alien inside of me?
Oh, I bet your teacher
sometimes thinks so.
Well, we have another question
from 8 year old Marrie.
Are you bringing the alien back to Earth?
No, we are gonna keep it up here.
We're gonna study it where it's safe.
Commander?
The ISS is the most
expensive house ever built.
200 billion American dollars and counting
because we keep adding rooms.
It flies around Earth 16 times a day.
In 30 years, over one hundred
people have lived here
thanks to generous countries
like Russia, the USA and China.
We call this Tranquility node.
Dr Jordan here is about to break the
record for consecutive days on space.
473 straight.
Your mommy must miss you.
She does, but I have family here.
Yeah, the kind that teases him
'cause his mommy misses him.
This is one of our newest crew members,
Miranda North
From the Centers for Disease Control.
She is a doctor too.
You guys are witnessing a space triathlon.
Yeah, I'm winning.
We have another question
from 7 year old Layla.
We think this question
is a little personal.
- Go ahead.
- How do you go to the bathroom?
Funnel.
Tube.
And some suction.
Everything we do on the ISS
is like everything you do on Earth.
- Except different. You like peas?
- Yeah.
Mmh.. boom!
So, have you got a name yet?
For that we wanna go down live,
just outside our studio in Time Square
to one very brave class mate.
- Hi, Dominique.
- Hi.
Calvin Coolidge Elementary
was chosen among 11.000 schools
for this honor.
We name the Martian
after our school.
"Calvin"
Control? Control?
If you're listening, and you probably are
'cause you're creepy that way
Can I just rant for a second
about the micromanagement?
We are not blood filled new puppets.
I come from a long line of plumbers.
I can fix a shower.
If I can't, well, Hugh doesn't
shower anyway. He's British.
- First international incident.
- Oh, I think, better cool you.
You're just a very underpaid
nation, everybody knows it.
- Don't be an ugly American.
- Wow, who's ugly now?
I nailed Step 17. I am a very
good looking American, you know.
Oh, I see, it's right there.
- Control, I'm sorry about him.
- Control can't hear you.
I don't know where rage
like that comes from.
Can you please just fix the shower?
You know, I can...
I can do this myself.
No, I know. You just haven't.
Doctors are always so bad at looking
after themselves, aren't they?
You've spent too much time up here, David.
Your atrophy has accelerated.
And you're close to radiation limit.
You noticed any...
glowing in the dark?
I like it up here.
When I was in the military, we go to Syria.
You know
We set up a hospital
Treat all the casualties, and then
We come back... a week
or two later, and the
whole village would
just be bombed out.
That Earth isn't all
Syria though, is it?
Can't stand what we do
to each other down there.
But it's home, and it's beautiful.
Don't you miss anything?
Don't you miss fresh water, or birds
the trees?
I like the hum up here.
And the air.
What you've achieved with
Calvin is remarkable, Hugh.
I haven't had a chance to say that.
Thank you. I think these will prove
to be greatest days of my life.
I wish I had a time machine,
so I could visit the 10 year old me.
Did he want to be an astronaut?
He wanted out of the wheelchair.
And how does he feel now?
Like a bird.
Oh, don't get me wrong.
I don't hate the chair.
I love it.
For the sake of the anonymous
genius who invented it.
You're one of a kind, Hugh.
Goodnight.
ISS, DAY 12
- 11:20 UTC.
- Hold on to your helmets.
The glucose intake is very rapid.
The specimen's cells have began
to move together on mass, as a unit.
And they've also shown
electrical activity
in what resembles
a growing neural network.
Notice I didn't say "brain".
Dr North speaking.
It's our educated opinion
that this new species
is not a colony of fast dividing
single celled organisms
but one larger solitary
organism composed of
trillions of
identical cooperative cells.
Here's what's fascinating...
I mean, it's all fascinating, isn't it?
Unlike most multi-cellular organisms
every cell of Calvin's can perform
every somatic function on its own.
Every single cell is simultaneously
a muscle cell and a nerve cell,
and a photo-receptive cell.
So the creature as a whole
is, in a very real sense, all muscle
all brain, all eye.
As such, Calvin now possesses the means
to interact with his environment
including the use of what
appears to be proto-appendages.
I'll demonstrate.
I notice how it's approaching
and not retreating.
Its curiosity outweighs its fear.
This is beautiful.
Hello, Calvin.
How does that feel, Hugh?
You're gonna be a daddy.
It's gonna be a big custody
battle over this one.
"And that there was more of it during
the night. We can observe too
how the recollection of a dream, which
was still lively in the morning
will melt away, except for
a few small fragments."
This book doesn't have
pictures in it, does it?
Obviously not.
Would you prefer that I
don't read it out loud?
I don't know, but
Guys, guys.
Meet Mei.
- Hi Mei!
- Hey Mei!
- Say hi to everybody, Mei.
- Hi Mei!
- She's beautiful!
- Congratulations!
- Thank you. "Nice to meet you".
- Do you have any idea who the father is?
- Shut up.
- Another one, another one.
Ok.
For story time.
It was my favorite.
You might say, my first
foray into space.
- Thank you so much.
- Thank you, Commander.
- Thank you guys.
- She's beautiful, Sho.
Thank you!
But seriously, that kid had blue eyes.
ISS, DAY 25
Fuck!
It's the lab.
Ok.
- Miranda, check the O2 in the lab.
- O2 is on 21. We're clear for contamination.
We're okay. Calvin is safe.
I don't understand how this happened.
Nothing in that lab can malfunction.
The clamp. It failed.
It's on me.
Yeah, no shit it's on you.
A dizzy 5 year old could've spotted that.
Protecting these firewalls, yes,
that's my job. But I can't do it alone.
Kibo wasn't designed for strict firewall
lockdown and neither was the station.
There is zero precedent for any of this.
But you do not come out of that lab
without triple checking everything.
You don't go in that lab
without a proper rest.
For all I know, we're
carrying Anthrax on board.
You can't compare Calvin to Anthrax.
Yeah, I know at least five guys
back home who could do my job.
Nobody can do yours except you.
I don't want to be around that thing.
I am not qualified to be around that thing.
I understand. I'm just saying you
can't compare Calvin to Anthrax.
Stop, stop calling it fukin' Calvin!
You don't know what that thing is.
Yeah?
You're in here and you're playing
around like it's your buddy.
I'm your buddy. You're drunk on this.
Wake up!
This isn't and will never be
a controlled experiment.
So let's all agree we made our
first and last mistake.
I miss my fucking dog!
Goodnight.
Dr Miranda North, quarantine officer,
23:20 UTC.
After weeks of stunning growth and activity,
Calvin is completely inactive.
We believe it's likely due to
the clamp failure in the lab
which caused a temporary change
of air pressure in Calvin's box.
Our working theory is that
this hibernation may be a defense mechanism.
Everyone here is on edge.
And Hugh of course has been beating
himself up, but honestly I'm relieved.
Calvin was growing very fast
and this is now giving me time to reinforce
firewall precautions with the crew.
The box must stay sealed.
The lab must stay sealed.
No matter the risk to Calvin.
It's just floating.
Because of my mistake, in the lab.
And it was going so well.
What?
It's something my dad used to say.
"It was all going so well."
I'm toying with the idea of stimulating
it electrically. What you think?
- That's not my call.
- But if it were?
I don't know.
My job is lines of defense.
Imagine the worst thing
that could have happened
and then the worse after that,
and the worse after that, and then I
I planned for all of them.
I understand that.
But risks are taken for reasons.
Because of Calvin, we could have
learned so much about life.
Its origin, its nature,
maybe even its meaning.
- Oh no, I know.
- You're a doctor. Stem cell research.
What if Calvin can make
stem cells obsolete?
Help cure the incurable?
Reverse the irreversible?
I have to fix this.
Good. You ready?
- Stretch.
- Okay.
And.. relax.
Ready.
- You sure it won't hurt it?
- It's a very very low voltage.
We're only stimulating it.
- What exactly are you hoping for?
- I'm hoping to wake him up.
We'll see under what conditions
it reengages with its environment.
Come on in.
We're hocking the monkey.
Trying another spot.
Nothing. Not even at
the cellular level.
Are you sure it's not, uh...
dead?
It's alive, it's just in a deep sleep.
Oh, Come on, Calvin.
Wake up.
Shit!
- What's wrong?
- It broke the wand.
I'm gonna try and pull my hand out.
Look, do that but just make
sure to protect the glove.
Shit. It's gripping the glass.
Okay, okay.
Little son of a...
- How hard is he holding on to you?
- Like a firm handshake.
- It's funny.
- It doesn't hurt, but it's damn strong.
- What's the problem?
- He's got Hugh's hand.
His heart rate is at 165.
- Sho. Can we trust the glove?
- It's very tight.
Glove is not going anywhere.
It's fine.
- Shit.
- Okay but, just relax. Tell him to relax.
Terry? Terry? Look at me.
Look at me. Relax.
Just relax your hand.
Ok.
Hes in between my fingers.
Can I make a suggestion? Can I just-
Can I go in there and get him out?
No, you're not gonna go in there!
No. Of course you're not, because
I have to maintaine quarantine.
You know, I can do this.
I can... I can do this.
- Can you try and distract it.
- Yes. Yes.
I'll see
if I can interest it in the wand.
Go on, my favorite little muffin.
Come on.
He lost interest.
He's got hold of my hand.
Argh!
Hugh?
Hey, Hugh!
- What the fuck is going on?
- No! No one is going in!
- Come on!
- Wait!
Who's going in?
- Waiting for fucking what?
- I'm going in there!
Don't, don't do this!
Ah... Argh!
I don't give a shit about your
fucking quarantine! We gotta-
Who gave you the fukin' jurisdiction?
Just open the door! Open!
Wait, wait, wait, wait!
He's out.
Guys, look at it.
- Oh, Jesus.
- What are his vitals?
126 and dropping.
What's it doing?
Holy shit.
Jesus Christ.
Okay.
You guys got eyes on it anywhere?
Hey, there. There.
Guys?
- Fuck this!
- No!
- Let him go.
- Hey buddy.
- Watch his hand.
- He's heavy.
Get him in!
Adams!
- Yeah.
- David, I need you here.
Rory.. I can't let you out.
Oh... shit!
Hugh, Hugh?
- Look at me.
- Just listen me for a second. Ok?
Hey guys?
- Suggestions?
- Get the oxygen candle! Burn it off!
Yeah, yeah, yeah yeah.
Fuck.
Okay. Alright. What now?
How do we get him out?
We need to get Calvin
back behind firewall 1.
And once he's there,
we can pull Rory out.
Fuck this. Permission...
to fucking kill the thing.
Commander?
Kill it.
Sho? Any suggestions?
- What about the incinerator?
- I like that. Alright. Genius. Here.
Close the red valve.
Disengage the clamp.
Disconnect the hose.
- Be careful, Rory.
- Fuck!
There is limited fuel.
- Manual override.
- Thank you.
Okay.
Rory, I...
Yeah.
Fuck!
You're wasting too much fuel.
Fuck.
Rory!
Rory? Hey!
Rory, stop. Stop!
Rory?
You're out of fuel.
It's behind you!
Jesus!
Fuck!
Somebody open up the fucking door!
And I'm gonna pull him out!
Just open up the door! There's a man
there that is getting strangled.
Rory? What are you saying?
Rory? Rory?
- Kat! We gotta open the door!
- No! It is the protocol!
What is this fucking protocol!
Just open the portal!
- Rory?
- There's a man dying in there!
Rory? Can you hear...
Calm down!
Rory?
We have a man dying in there!
Guys?
Guys.
Sho.
It's so much bigger.
Jesus!
- Guys?
- Sho.
Guys, it's trying to get out.
- The CPU overruled us.
- It's searching for a way out.
- The system won't give me access to it.
- Go manual.
Shut them down. Okay?
- How smart is this thing?
- It feels the air flow.
- I can't control them all at once.
- Then shut them one by one.
Seal the lab!
- Shut it down. Shut it down now!
- We're on it.
Guys, it's gone.
- It got out.
- Where did it go?
Could be anywhere now.
Firewall 2 has failed.
Kat
We need to re-establish quarantine.
I'll get a distress call out.
Control, this is Station.
Station to Control.
The specimen's location is unknown.
It is to be considered
hostile and deadly.
Our intent is to isolate and destroy it
in compliance with protocol.
We will continue said course of action
unless otherwise instructed.
- Please acknowledge and advice.
- Kat.
We lost them.
- How much of that went out?
- Some.. I think.
There is no way to be sure.
Looks like communications just failed.
Can we talk to each other?
David?
It's Kat.
Do you copy?
Go for David.
- Still, we've lost contact with Earth.
- I dont think...
Wait.
- Yes, outside communications are down.
- Could the sprinklers affect comms?
No. They are independent systems.
Can we run a diagnostic from here?
The transmitter has failed.
But, we have to go outside to access it
and get Earth back online.
Then I have to walk.
Let me.
No.
After Rory, I'm best qualified
for walk and repair.
This is not protocol. It's way
too risky for you go out there
to fix the comms.
We don't know where Calvin is.
Haven't had your Nitrogen detox.
Your health is my responsibility.
- I'll be fine.
- Yep.
What is it you say?
"Slow is fast", right?
- Yeah. "Slow to go fast."
- Yeah.
Well, that's out the window.
We can escape in our lifeboats.
Earth is the responsibility.
Nothing goes down to the planet.
It was stipulated in writing.
What are you talking about?
What was stipulated in a writing?
What was stipulated?
David, first things first.
When we're back in touch with Control,
we'll turn our attention to Calvin.
Don't worry.
Rate: 61 beats per minute.
Pressure: 97/53.
I'd hate to see you relaxed.
But she is relaxed.
Aren't you, Kat?
Suit's running warm.
Like Siberia in summer.
I'm at the transmitter.
Commencing on site diagnostics.
It overheated.
I can tell.
How?
I see scorching.
I will pitch up the coolant levels.
Is it possible Calvin
could've gotten into coolant?
- Possible.
- We have to know.
- There is the issue.
- Commander?
It's bone dry.
Calvin is a carbon-based organism.
It needs food, water,
and oxygen. Just like us.
We have to consider the possibility
it consumed the coolant for food.
David, could you list all the water
sources aboard? Pure or otherwise.
There is plenty of drinking water.
There's coolant for the comms,
coolant for the CPU
and there is coolant for the..
Commander?
Calvin just came out,
then grabbed to my suit.
It's bigger.
- It's trying to get in.
- Trust your suit.
- Can it breathe out there?
- No.
But it might be able to store
oxygen for a period of time.
I'm closing the valve.
- It's squeezing.
- Kat, Kat. Are you okay?
Yes. The suit is thick enough.
It's twisting up your leg.
Go, go to the airlock now.
Oh, fuck this. I'm headed to the airlock.
I'll burn this fucker off!
Kat. Focus on meeting David.
We will worry about the comms later.
Sho?
There is liquid in the helmet. Calvin
must have broken my coolant tube.
- Kat, there is enough coolant.
- Yes I know.
I know.
David... meet me at the airolck.
What? Yeah. Go, go, go!
It's is squeezing harder.
Calvin cracked the cooling
system in her suit.
Commander. Calvin knows
exactly what he is doing.
It's growing smarter.
The liquid is blocking my vision.
I don't have time.
I've got to jump.
- Kat, the tether won't reach.
- I'm unclipping.
- Kat?
- No comments. I've got to jump.
David, I've taken care of the channel.
She is not gonna tell you, but her
heart is beating out of her chest.
She is drowning. So just be
prepared, she may not be rational.
Copy that.
Sho, I got no time for EVA.
Using the launch suit.
- It's not designed for this.
- I know.
There's not enough protection.
- I know, don't worry.
- Kat is less than a minute out.
- Check the airlock!
- What about decompression?
- Just do it!
- It's gonna hurt.
- Come on, do it!
- Is your helmet sealed?
Sho!
Guys, we're running out of time.
- Kat. Kat.
- Don't swallow it. It's toxic, okay?
I need you to help me open the valve.
We'll do it together, okay?
I'm gonna pull down, and you're
gonna go clockwise from your side.
Okay? There you go.
Good, good, good.
Don't worry about Calvin.
We are gonna get you inside and get it off.
Kat?
No, clockwise from your side!
Clockwise from your side!
Kat, come on!
- Miranda?
- Yeah, I'm here.
She's fighting me!
She's turned the lever the wrong way!
Hold..
Kat, you're fighting me Kat.
Come on!
- We gotta do it together now! Come on!
- David?
Kat, come on, please!
Kat, come on...
- Kat.
- Look at me!
- Kat!
- Just pull on the lever, okay?
Kat, come on!
Come on!
Just pull down on the lever!
- David, she...
- Kat! Come on, you can do this!
David, she's doing it deliberately.
Come on!
Kat!
- Kat!
- David, stop.
Stop.
She's not letting
Calvin back in here.
Kat.
Commander...
Kat. Kat.
What's going on?
What is going on?
Guys, guys, do you copy?
- Yeah, yeah I copy.
- Okay, okay...
Just keep it together.
We may have...
We may have an opportunity here.
Calvin's ability to survive in that
vacuum and temperature is astonishing.
But it can't live
much longer out there.
Sho? Sho?
Are you sure that we've lost
all communication with Earth?
I am sure.
Alright then.
We have to keep him out there.
We have a new firewall.
David. Can you see it?
I'm seeing... Sho?
- Yes.
- Can you re-flood the airlock?
You tell me when.
Okay.
Did she close that valve?
Oh, yeah, yeah she closed it.
Ok.
What are the ways through he get in?
The thrusters.
The manifolds in the thruster nozzles.
If he tries one, we could blast it off.
But we'd have to know which.
It's too dark.
I can't see anything.
There must be some way.
Thruster sensors.
If it climbs in the nozzle,
the temperature should move.
Should.
Alright.
- There!
- Thruster 2. Firing.
Miranda, can you reach Tranquility?
We missed! Cut it!
Guys, it's heading toward that way.
No, no! It's heading towards the lab!
It's fast!
- I'm sorry, guys, I can't see.
- It's okay, we'll watch it.
- Kibo.
- Thruster 3. Firing.
Come on!
Please, please.
- Thruster 5. David, can you see it?
- Thruster 5.
Sho?
- What was that?
- We've burnt through too much fuel.
- There.
- We were already low after the Pilgrim.
Doc, listen. All this thrusting...
We've placed ourselves
into decaying orbit.
Shit.
We'll reach atmosphere soon,
if I don't get us back to stable.
And I'll need the rest of the fuel
to do it, if we even have that much.
No. David?
David, we can't risk Calvin riding
us down into the atmosphere. Ok?
I don't know if it could
have survived it.
We don't know.
He's already gone well beyond
what any living organism
should be able to survive.
If it's between letting it in here,
or letting it down there...
We let it in here.
Where are you?
We've just let it back in here.
Moving us back into stable orbit.
These creatures could have dominated
Mars for hundreds of millions of years.
But now we know that they hibernate
for the loss of atmosphere.
If we deprive it of air, retreat to
Tranquility and seal ourselves off
And vent the rest of the station.
Exactly.
No life support, no life.
Right.
Ok, Hugh and I will
sweep from quest east.
And...
You and Sho scout the poles and
lock off each compartment.
This will take about...
four hours to vent all oxygen.
- What do we do till then?
- We wait.
You okay?
Derry, look at me. You okay?
I'm fine.
I remember the day the
Challenger blew up.
They took us out of school early.
I remember that day.
It's hard to watch people die.
Like...
Fireworks.
Up, up.
A long, delirious, burning blue.
I topped the windswept heights
with ease and grace.
- Best eulogy ever.
Rory'd say us:
"Don't give me an eulogy."
"Give me a parachute."
He was my buddy.
It's my fault.
It's all my fault.
Maybe it was your fault, maybe
it was my fault. Maybe.
I know it doesn't matter, does it?
Getting this thing onboard was a risk
and we knew it from the beginning.
We took it.
It's just surviving.
Life's very existence
requires destruction.
Calvin doesn't hate us.
But he has to kill us
in order to survive.
Hugh.
I don't know, I don't know.
Hey, Hugh.
It's fine.
Sorry, because of all the...
- Hugh?
There is no output.
Kat. Get the defib.
Get him right. Okay.
- Get him down.
- I'll strap him in.
- Take off the sling. Okay?
- Yeah.
Sho, get the ACLS kit
and the defibrillator.
Shit.
Here.
Prep the defibrillator
and get the shocks now.
- 360 joules.
- Copy, 360 joules. Charging.
Clear.
- Charging.
- Still defibrillator in.
Just stuck the shocks if you have to.
Go, 360!
Alright. Clear!
- Nothing.
- Go again. 360.
- Go Again, hit him.
- Clear.
Alright.
- Okay output.
- Yeah?
Ok, sinus rate: 98 beats pm.
You really scared me there, buddy.
David?
- What is this?
- Stabilizing.
- Get the plasma cutter.
- Calvin's feeding off his leg.
Go. Get out of here.
- Let's go!
- Come on!
Miranda, let's go!
Pull away from Hugh!
- We'll come back for him!
- Let's go!
Sho!
No!
- Sho!
- No!
Guys?
- Calvin?
- We don't know where he is.
- Where is Sho?
- He'll be fine.
We stopped all oxygen venting
in the station.
Lift me up.
Oh.. Miranda.
Up, up.
I'm coming home, Mei.
You know what I feel is not scientific.
It's not rational.
I feel hate.
I feel pure...
fucking...
hate for that thing.
Calvin.
How is that moving like that?
He must have swallowed
the  marker on Derry's leg.
Yeah.
We can track it.
Let's kill this thing!
Lifting "Zarya" now.
Ok, it's suffocating. How long
do you think that's gonna take?
I don't know.
Proximity alert.
They're coming.
Kat's distress call must have reached Earth.
Right, where are they docking?
- Shit. Looks like "Zarya".
- Jesus, that's where Calvin is.
Station to "Soyuz".
Station to "Soyuz", do you copy?
- Station to "Soyuz", do you copy?
- Try the flashlight.
Come on, come on!
They can't see this.
Must be too reflective.
Shit. What the fuck are they doing?
David.
David!
They are not coming to rescue us.
- It's firewall 3.
- What?
Firewall 1 was the box.
The firewall 2 was the lab.
The firewall 3 is the station.
- But we have a new firewall.
- They don't know that.
And if firewall 1 or 2 fail,
they have two choices.
They can contain..
or they expel.
They're pushing us out to deep space.
They cannot risk
Calvin reaching Earth.
It was my protocol.
I insisted from the beginning,
and the committee agreed.
They all put their names to it.
The list is as long as your arm.
Look, protective firewalls is my job.
And if we would have succeeded,
we could have gone home.
And if we fail...
Wait for me, Mei.
Sho. Oh, he thinks it's a rescue.
God! He's heading towards Calvin.
Sho! Sho, can you hear us?
Sho!
- Sho!
- Take my hand!
Don't let go Sho!
No, don't, don't  let go!
No! No! No! No!
- No!
- Let go!
No! Sho!
Miranda!
The CPU is still up.
It's a miracle.
We're..
We're losing life support.
The temperature is dropping rapidly.
Atmosphere's venting from everywhere,
and I don't know how to stop it.
- Ok, how much time do we have?
- In here?
Two hours, maybe an hour and 45.
I need a...
- What?
- Fuck.
- Fuck. Fuck.
- What ? What is it?
- What?
- We're...
We're not moving into space.
The opposite.
All that fucked up thrusting,
we are decaying again.
What?
Sho has a subroutine here.
Without any correction in course, which
we don't have any fuel for anyway...
We'll hit the atmosphere in...
39 minutes.
We're not gonna survive re-entry.
But Calvin could.
It's so cold.
My father used to read this to me
when I was a kid.
Goodnight, room.
Goodnight, Moon.
Good night, cow jumping over the moon.
Good night, light
and the red balloon.
Goodnight, nobody.
I remember when I saw
my first picture of Earth.
And I asked my father
where all those...
all those lines were.
The borders.
I really miss him.
"Good night, Moon"
"Good night, stars"
"Good night, air"
Bait.
Calvin needs oxygen to survive.
With the O2 level so low in the rest of
the ship, it will drawning oxygen candles.
We can use them as bait.
There are two lifeboats, A and B.
Both set to default entry trajectory.
You press the button, they
autopilot themselves to the surface.
Unless somebody...
somebody overrides them from the inside.
I'll use the oxygen candles
to lure Calvin into boat A.
I close the hatch, you press the button
to give me full manual control.
If I can hold the stick
I can override the flight path.
And I hold it long enough,
it will avoid re-entry.
- You fly it into deep space.
- With.. With Calvin. Yes.
Meanwhile, you get into boat B.
You press the button.
and if there are no complications,
it'd take you back home.
- No, we should lure Calvin together.
- Come on, Miranda.
- It doesn't make any sense.
- Why?
It is just that the lifeboats
are meant for one person.
And this has been your plan all along.
To make sure that creature
doesn't get to Earth.
- Then I should be Plan A.
- No, I'm the pilot.
You're Plan B.
Listen, listen.
I belong up here.
I dont wanna go back down there
living with those motherfuckers.
I need you to say you trust me.
Yeah?
I do.
I trust you.
Wait here. I'll signal you.
Shit!
Fuck.
This is mission specialist Dr David Jordan
commanding "Soyuz" lifeboat A.
22:33 UTC.
The ISS has entered
catastrophic orbital decay.
Initiating emergency
escape sequence in...
Come on, Miranda, get going.
Initiating manual override.
This is Dr Miranda North, black box
recording, in case of death upon re-entry.
The creature killed four
of the six ISS astronauts
with fifth, Dr David Jordan, presumed
dead, carrying it out into deep space.
My five colleagues all sacrificed
themselves to maintain the firewalls.
So, please, honor them for giving
everything to this cause.
Mars life forms should be
considered hostile.
Do not underestimate their intelligence
and their adaptive capabilities.
Now, we did not learn how to
restrain or eliminate it...
and if this creature
ever reaches Earth...
use every available resource
to destroy it...
or you will risk all human life.
No, no! Don't!
Noo! Noo!
No! No!
Don't!
No, no, no!